<chapter id="colophon">
  <title>
    Colophon
  </title>

  <para>
    You now know how to make a complete game in Python with the Pygame
    libraries. If you want to go farther, then here are the next steps&#58;
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Start learning Linux. Especially in terms of programming,
	Linux is the most powerful tool available. Not only can you
	see all the code making your computer run &#40;because Linux
	and all of its tools itself is open source&#41;, but you have
	easy access to all the latest developments for graphics and
	device drivers. Valve &#40;creators of Steam&#41; and Vulkan
	&#40;formerly OpenGL&#41; use Linux as a base platform for a
	reason.
      </para>
      <para>If you&#39;re not sure how to get started, buy a book
      about getting started with Fedora Linux, and step through it. As
      a quick introduction, see the website <ulink
      url="http://klaatu.multics.org/switch">Switch to Linux</ulink>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Practise makes perfect. Go make another platformer. After
      that, make yet another, but this time challenge yourself to come
      up with something you don&#39;t know how to do yet.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>When in doubt, read the <ulink
      url="https://docs.python.org/3/">Python 3 docs</ulink> and
      the <ulink url="https://www.pygame.org/docs">Pygame
      docs</ulink>. They aren&#39;t always easy to understand right
      away, but between reading them and looking online or within
      your Linux OS for sample code, you&#39;ll pick up all kinds of
      new tricks. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>When you&#39;re comfortable with Pygame, look for
      what&#39;s next. When you&#39;re a programmer, you&#39;re also a
      student, always learning new things. You can safely stay with
      Python, because Python is used by nearly every industry out
      there, but there&#39;s a lot more to Python than just Pygame, so
      go learn it. Write your own Python libraries. Learn PyQt, and
      Numpy, and Cython. Move forward&#33;
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <section id="about">
    <title>About this book</title>

    <para>
      This book was written in <ulink
      url="http://docbook.org">Docbook 5</ulink>, an XML schema. It
      was written on <ulink
      url="http://slackware.com">Slackware</ulink> Linux in the
      <application
      url="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/emacs.html">Emacs</application>
      text editor.
    </para>

    <para>
      This book is licensed under the <ulink
      url="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative
      Commons Attribution-ShareAlike International 4.0</ulink>
      license. This means that you are free to share the book with
      others, or even modify it. If you modify it, you must use the
      same license to ensure others have the same freedom as you
      have. See the full license for a complete description.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  </chapter>

</book>