<chapter id="intro">
  <title>
    Intro to Python
  </title>

  <para>
    Python is an all-purpose programming language. It can be used to
    create desktop applications, 3d graphics, video games, and even
    websites. It's a good language to learn because it's simpler than
    complex languages like C, C++, or Java, but is almost as powerful,
    and is used in just about every industry that uses computers.
  </para>

  <para>
    Unlike Scratch, Python doesn't have a GUI. You have to type code
    into a text editor, save the file, and then run it with the Python
    interpreter.
  </para>

<mediaobject>
  <info>
    <othercredit>
      <orgname>MakerBox</orgname>
    </othercredit>
    <othercredit>
      <orgname>MIT</orgname>
    </othercredit>
  </info>
  <alt>Scratch and Python</alt>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata align="left" format="JPG"
	       fileref="topics/images/scratchLikePython.jpg"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject>
    <para>
    The Scratch interface is like Python. The Scratch scripts and you
    make with Scratch blocks are like Python code.      
    </para>
  </textobject>
</mediaobject>

<section id="intro_install">
  <title>
    Installing Python
  </title>

  <para>
    Before learning Python, you may need to install it.
  </para>

  <bridgehead>
    Linux
  </bridgehead>
  
      <para>
	If you use <ulink url="http://getfedora.org">Linux</ulink>, Python is already included, but make sure that you have <code>Python 3</code>, specifically. To check what version you have installed, open a terminal window and type&#58;
      </para>

      <code>
	python3 -V
      </code>

      <para>
	If that command is not found, then install Python 3 from your package manager.
      </para>

  <bridgehead>
    Mac OS
  </bridgehead>

  <para>
    Follow the instructions for Linux, above. Macintosh does not have
    an inbuilt package manager, so if Python 3 is not found, install
    it from <ulink
    url="https://www.python.org/downloads/mac-osx/">python.org&#47;downloads&#47;mac-osx</ulink>.
  </para>

  <bridgehead>
    Windows
  </bridgehead>

  <para>
    At the time of this writing, Microsoft Windows doesn&#39;t yet ship with Python. Install it from <ulink url="https://www.python.org/downloads/windows">python.org&#47;downloads&#47;windows</ulink>. Be sure to select <guilabel>Add Python to PATH</guilabel> in the install wizard.
  </para>
    
</section>

<section id="intro_start-python">
  <title>
    Starting Python 3
  </title>

  <para>
    Since you&#39;ve never used Python before, your first task is to try a
    few simple one-line programmes with it. You can talk directly to
    Python by running it in a terminal. 
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	On Linux or macOS, launch a terminal window and type <command>python3</command> 
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
	On Windows, launch Python 3 from the Start menu.
      </para>
      <para>
	If there is no Python in the Start menu, launch Windows
	PowerShell and type <command>C&#58;\Windows\py.exe</command>
      </para>
      <para>
	If that doesn&#39;t work, try reinstalling Python. Be sure to select <guilabel>Add Python to PATH</guilabel> in the install wizard. Refer to <ulink url="https://docs.python.org/3/using/windows.html">docs.python.org/3/using/windows.html</ulink> for detailed instructions.
      </para>
      <para>
	If that doesn&#39;t work, make sure you have Python installed, or
	just use <ulink
	url="https://getfedora.org/en_GB/workstation/download/">Linux</ulink>. It's
	free and doesn't even require you to install it to use it.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id="intro_python-commands">
  <title>
    Telling Python what to do
  </title>

  <para>
    Just like Scratch has code blocks, Python has keywords that tell
    Python what you want it to do.
  </para>

  <para>
    For instance, type this at your Python prompt and then press <keycode>Return</keycode>&#58;
  </para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
    >>> print("Hello world.")
    Hello world.
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>
    The keyword <command>print</command> tells Python to print out
    whatever text you give it in parentheses and quotes.
  </para>

  <para>
    That's not very exciting, though. Unlike Scratch, which has
    probably 100 code blocks ready to use, Python only
    has access to some basic keywords, like <command>print</command>,
    <command>help</command>, and so on.
  </para>

  <para>
    Use the <command>import</command> keyword to load more keywords.
  </para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
    >>> import turtle
  ]]></programlisting>

  <para>
    Turtle is a fun module to use. It&#39;s exactly like the Pen code
    blocks in Scratch.
  </para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
    >>> turtle.begin_fill()
    >>> turtle.forward(100)
    >>> turtle.left(90)
    >>> turtle.forward(100)
    >>> turtle.left(90)
    >>> turtle.forward(100)
    >>> turtle.left(90)
    >>> turtle.forward(100)
    >>> turtle.end_fill()
  ]]></programlisting>

  <section id="intro_exercise">
    <title>Exercise</title>

    <para>
      See what shapes you can draw with the turtle module.
    </para>

    <para>
      To clear you turtle drawing area, use the
      <command>turtle.clear&#40;&#41;</command> keyword.
    </para>

    <para>
      What do you think the keyword
      <command>turtle.color&#40;&#34;blue&#34;&#41;</command> does?
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

  <section id="intro_script">
    <title>Scripting Python</title>
    
    <para>
      Now that you&#39;ve had a chance to play around with Python 3 in the
      terminal, it&#39;s time to write a Python script. 
    </para>

    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
	<question>
	  <para>What is a script in Scratch?</para>
	</question>
	<answer>
	  <para>It&#39;s a list of instructions that controls your programme.</para>
	</answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>

    <para>
      A script in Python 3 is a lot like a script in Scratch. The
      difference is that instead of using code blocks, Python 3 uses
      keywords.
    </para>

    <para>
      To write a Python script, you must have a text editor.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  If you use <emphasis>Linux</emphasis>, you can use whatever
	  editor is already included &#40;common ones are gedit, kate,
	  and mousepad&#41;. Alternately, you can try something more
	  advanced, like <ulink url="atom.io">Atom</ulink> or <ulink
	  url="http://gnu.org/software/emacs">Emacs</ulink>.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  On <emphasis>Mac OS</emphasis>, do not use Text&nbsp;Edit,
	  because it&#39;s not Python-aware, and it sometimes fails to
	  save files as text. Instead, use <ulink
	  url="http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/GNOME/binaries/mac/gedit/3.2/gedit-3.2.6.dmg">gedit</ulink>
	  or <ulink url="atom.io">Atom</ulink>
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  On Windows, you can use Notepad, but it&#39;s not Python-aware. try a good text editor like <ulink
	  url="https://notepad-plus-plus.org">Notepad++</ulink> or
	  <ulink url="atom.io">Atom</ulink>.
	</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Open an empty text file and type this programme. In Python, the
      indentation matters, so type this exactly as you see it, using
      the <keycode>Tab</keycode> key to indent when necessary.
    </para>


    <programlisting><![CDATA[
      import turtle as t
      import time
      
      t.color("blue")
      t.begin_fill()

      n=0
      
      while n < 4:
          t.forward(100)
          t.left(90)
      
      t.end_fill()
      time.sleep(5)
    ]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      Save the text file as <filename>turtle.py</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      To run your script, type <command>python3
      $MOHE/turtle.py</command> on Linux or macOS. On Windows, type
      <command>Python.exe turtle.py</command>
    </para>

    <para>
      Once you have run your script, it&#39;s time to explore an even
      better module. One popular module used to create video games with Python
      is called PyGame. It&#39;s got a lot more features than turtle,
      but is also a lot more complex, so be prepared.
    </para>
  </section>

<section id="intro_install">
  <title>
    Installing Pygame
  </title>

  <para>
    Before continuing into the exciting world of Pygame, you must install it first. Pythen 3, like Linux, has a <firstterm>package manager</firstterm> that lets you install extra modules from the Internet.
  </para>

  <para>
    To install Pygame with Python 3, open a terminal window &#40;on Windows, open Windows PowerShell&#41;&#58;
  </para>

  <screen>
    pip3 install pygame
  </screen>

  <para>
    If you&#39;re on Windows, you might need to use this instead &#40;it depends on how you installed Python&#41;&#58;
  </para>
  
  <screen>
    C&#58;\Windows\py.exe -m &#39;pip&#39; install pygame --user
  </screen>

</section>
</chapter>
