<chapter id="preface">
  <title>
    Who should read this book
  </title>

  <para>
    This book is intended for <ulink
    url="https://www.raspberrypi.org/learning/getting-started-with-scratch/worksheet">Scratch</ulink>
    users who are looking to graduate to a more advanced programming
    environment to make even more advanced games. It is written for
    <emphasis>both</emphasis> students and teachers, because
    everyone&#39;s a student at some point, and everyone can become a
    teacher.
  </para>

  <para>
    <ulink url="https://www.python.org/">Python</ulink> is a
    popular open source language that is used in the majority of tech
    industries, including 3d modeling, filmmaking, desktop
    applications, IT, security, and gaming. It&#39;s an important
    language to learn, but it&#39;s also one of the easiest languages
    to learn because it&#39;s designed specifically to be clear and
    simple.
  </para>

  <section id="preface_ready">
    <title>Are you ready for Python?</title>
    
  <para>
    While Python is simpler than an advanced language like C++,
    it&#39;s also a serious, professional-level language. It requires
    you to type out code, to keep files organised, and to debug.
  </para>

  <para>
    Everyone has their own programming style, so there&#39;s no
    way to tell you exactly how you know when you&#39;re ready to
    graduate to Python. Here are some traits of a Scratch user who is
    probably ready to graduate to Python&#58;
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Your games are getting too big or too complex for Scratch.
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
	You are comfortable using variables in Scratch.
      </para>
    </listitem>
	
    <listitem>
      <para>
	You find dragging and dropping blocks in Scratch slow and
	inefficient, and frequently look for ways to build your
	scripts faster.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    If any of those characteristics are familiar to you, then you are
    probably ready to tackle Python. However, you shouldn&#39;t feel
    that you <emphasis>have to</emphasis> start Python unless you want
    to. While it&#39;s true that you aren&#39;t going to get any jobs
    making games if all you know is Scratch, it&#39;s also true that
    Scratch is a lot of fun, and very powerful. Python is fun, too,
    and it does get easier, but it starts out hard. It takes work, and
    lots of practise. The most important thing is to keep programming
    fun, and you&#39;re free to move at your own pace. 
  </para>

  <para>
    If you are ready to learn something new, then this book is for
    you.
  </para>
  
  </section>
</chapter>
